A third of the
land on our planet is desert
These great scars
on the face of the earth
appear to
be lifeless
But surprisingly
none are
In all of them
life manages somehow
to keep a
precarious hold
Not all
deserts are hot
50 mile an hour
winds blowing in from Siberia
bring snow to the
Gobi Desert in Mongolia
From a summer
high of 50 degrees centigrade
the temperature
in midwinter can drop to minus 40
making this one
of the harshest deserts of all
Few animals can
survive these extreme changes
Wild Bactrian camels
one of the rarest
mammals on the planet
And perhaps
the hardiest
Their biggest
problem is the lack of water
particularly
now in winter
when the little
there is is locked up as ice
Surprisingly
snow here
never melts
The air is just
too cold and too dry for it to do so
The sun's rays
turn it straight into vapour
It evaporates
But it is the
only source of water
So Bactrian
camels eat it
Elsewhere
in the world
a camel at a waterhole can drink as much as 200 litres
during a
single visit
Here
the strategy is
to take little and often
and with
good reason
For filling the
stomach with snow
could be fatal
The camels must
limit themselves
to the equivalent
of just ten litres a day
Winter is the
time for breeding
This extraordinary performance
is a male
Bactrian camel's way
of attracting the
attention of a passing female
In summer
the camels can't
stray far from waterholes
But now
with mouthfuls of
snow lying everywhere
They can travel
widely in search of mates
Today
less than a thousand of these desert specialists
remain in the wild
The Gobi
hostile
though it is
is their
last stronghold
There is no other
desert quite like the Gobi
But why is this
place a desert？
There is one
simple and massive cause
the Himalayas
Clouds blowing
from the south hit this gigantic barrier
As they're
forced upwards
so they empty
their moisture on the mountain slopes
Leaving little
for the land on the other side
From space
deserts are
very conspicuous
Dunes of sand hundreds of miles long streak their surface
With no cloak of
vegetation to conceal them
Strange formations are exposed in the naked rock
Africa's Sahara
is the largest desert of all
It's the size of
the United States
And the biggest
source of sand and dust
In the
entire world
Sandstorms like
these appear without warning
And reduce visibility for days over areas the size of Britain
Dromedaries
single
humped camels
take these
storms in their stride
The heavy sand
rises only a few metres above the ground
But the dust can
be blown 5000 metres up into the sky
The ferocious wind
armed with
grains of sand
is the agent that
shapes all deserts
Reptiles have
armoured， scaly skins
that protect them
from the stinging grazes
For insects
the bombardment
can be very severe indeed
The only escape
is below the surface
As the winds
rise and fall
swirl and eddy
So they pile the
sand into dunes
These sand seas
can be hundreds of miles across
In Namibia
the winds have
built some of the biggest dunes in the world
Star dunes like
these can be 300 metres high
Grains swept
up the flanks
are blown off the
crests of the ridges
So it's only the
tops that are moving
The main body of
these dunes may not have shifted for 5000 years
Few rocks can
resist the continuous blast
of the sand
carrying wind
These outcrops
are standing in Egypt's white desert
But they will not
do so for much longer
They're being
inexorably chiselled away
and turned
into more sand
Now
lumps of heavily
eroded rocks have been marooned
in a sea of sand
These
jagged pyramids
100 metres tall
were once part of
a continuous rocky plateau
The blasting sand
will eventually eliminate them altogether
The relentless
power of the wind
ensures that the
face of a desert is continually changing
But there is one
constant presence
The desert sun
The sun's heat
and power to evaporate water
has had a profound effect on the bodies and habits
of everything
that lives here
This sun
potentially is a killer
And the red
kangaroos must acknowledge that
Right now
while the
sun is low
there's no
immediate cause for concern
But this
situation won't last long
Australia is the
world's most arid continent
With blistering
daytime temperatures
Every hour
the temperature
rises by five degrees centigrade
Soon
the heat will
reach a critical point
Any kangaroo
out in the open
is in serious
danger of overheating
In the full sun
the temperature
on the ground soars to 70 degrees
By midday
the radiation
is so intense
they must
take shelter
In the shade
they're shielded
from much of the sun's energy
But their body
temperature can still rise
So they lick
saliva onto their forearms
Where there is a network of blood vessels close to the surface of the skin
And as the
saliva evaporates
their
blood is cooled
This thermal image shows just how effective the process is
The blue areas on
the body are the cooler parts
As the
saliva dries
it has to
be replaced
And this is a
real drain on the kangaroo's body fluids
Even in the shade
the earth
is baking hot
So the kangaroos
dig away the warmed topsoil
To get at the
cooler ground beneath
By staying
in the shade
and licking to
control their body temperature
kangaroos manage
to get through the hottest part of the day
without
heat stroke
But for the
majority of desert animals
this strategy
would not be enough for survival
The extraordinary
ears of the panic foxes of Africa radiate heat
But the animals
have another way of keeping cool
They spend their
days underground
and only
emerge at sunset
Darkness
brings huge changes
In the Sahara
the temperature
can drop as much as 30 degrees during the night
So it's cool enough to allow these desert fox cubs to play
All sorts of
creatures now appear
including some
really unexpected ones
Toads have
permeable skins
and would quickly
die from desiccation out in the daytime heat
It's only now
that they can leave shelter
The same is
true for scorpions
even though their
shells are actually watertight
In fact
most small
desert creatures are nocturnal
So it's only now
that you can judge
just how much
life there can be in a desert
But moisture
lost even at night
has to be
replaced sometime
somehow
And that problem
dominates the lives
of all
desert dwellers
The Atacama in Chile
This is the
driest desert in the world
Some parts may
not see rain for 50 years
And with
such a record
you would expect
the place to be completely barren
These are South
America's camels
Huanacos
They're very good
at conserving moisture
but they nonetheless need a regular supply of water
They get it
partly from cactus flowers
But that explanation raises another question
How do the cacti
survive without rain？
Hot winds suck all the moisture from the surface of the land
Clearly
there must be something else that takes the place of rain
The secret is a
cold sea current that runs parallel to the land
The cold water
cools the moist warm air above it
and that
produces banks of fog
At the same time
wind blowing
onto the shore sweeps the fog inland
Before long
the cacti are
dripping with dew
The fog is
so regular
that moistureloving lichens are able to grow on the cacti
and they absorb
liquid like a sponge
In a land of
almost no rain
these precious
drops are lifesavers
for many
different creatures
Further inland
the air
remains so warm
that its moisture
does not condense
So this slender
strip of desert
is virtually the
only part of the Atacama
where life
can exist
And without the fog
this land too
would be empty
The huarnacos
make the most of the dew
But it will not
remain for long
In an hour or two
the sun will
have burnt it off
and dried the
surface of the cacti
The Sonoran
desert in Arizona
is not quite so
dry as the Atacama
Some rain
does fall
But it is
infrequent
And when it
does arrive
Animals and plants have to be ready to make the most of it
And it's coming
When the summer
monsoon blows in
The giant saguaro
one of the
biggest of all cacti
Are ready to take
full advantage of it
After a rainstorm
the sawaow's long
shallow root system sucks up the water
And the pleats on
its trunk enable it to expand rapidly
When full
a sawara stem
can store up to five tons of water
And that's enough
to see it through many months of drought
The trunks of
these huge plants
provide homes for
the keela woodpecker
But birds are not
the only animals to benefit
from the
presence of the cacti
During four
weeks of the summer
the sawaros
bloom at night
to attract visitors
The pollen and
nectar with which these flowers are loaded
attract longnosed
and longtongued bats
The bats left
Mexico a few days earlier
to escape the
heat of summer
and are on
their way north
to the southern United States
To get there
they have to
cross the Sonoran Desert
But the
desert is so big
That for
most of the year
They would be
unable to cross it
Now
with the
sowara in bloom
They can
refuel on the way
So the Soweto's
success in developing a way to store water
is now crucial to
most of the animals that live
or even travel
through this land
The scarcity of rain determined the shape of this icon of the desert
But water
scarcely
though it is
has also
like the wind
shaped the
land itself
In the
deserts of Utah
Ancient rivers
flowing across sandstone country
steadily
widened their canyons
Until now
the land
between them
has been reduced
to spires and pinnacles
With little or no
soil to retain the water on the surface of the land
life here is
scarce indeed
And when
resources are limited
conflict is
never far away
These are
Nubian ibexes
and they're
squaring up for a duel
And when
trouble starts
a smart ibex
knows that the best thing to do
is to gain
higher ground
These are actually subordinate male ibex
but their fights
are none the less serious
Losing one might
mean never getting the chance to breed
ever
When competitors
are evenly matched
as they are here
duels can
last for an hour
In this heat
the effort is
truly exhausting
But victory here
will gain
important ranking points
On a male's
way to the top
There's so
much at stake
That not
all play fair
The battle has
produced a winner
But the ultimate
prize is not his yet
That currently
belongs to the dominant male ibex
His rank earns
him the loyalty of a harem of females
And they
follow him closely
As he travels
across this desert
Searching for
food and water
He doesn't have
to waste time looking for mates
They're his
for the taking
So he can
concentrate with them
On keeping
fit and healthy
Lizards are
desert specialists
But here their
numbers are extraordinary
These crevices
in South Africa
contain the highest density of lizards in the world
They're called
flat lizards for obvious reasons
And they flaunt
their multicoloured bellies
In territorial disputes
He's made
his point
And now it's time
to find some food
As the
day warms up
The lizards move
away from their cracks
And head down to
the bottom of the gorge
Their goal
is the river
There is no
food at the edge
But this desert
river holds a secret
Each day
black fly rise
from turbulent stretches of the river
This is what the
lizards have come for
The blackfly never land
so the lizards
have to leap for their food
In one day
each of these
acrobatic little lizards
may catch 50 flies
There are plenty
of flies to go round
even with hundreds of lizards competing for them
Away from
these rapids
flat lizard
populations
are found in
much smaller numbers
But here
one unusual
abundance has produced another
Deserts are
created by the lack of water
But what actually
kills animals here
is not
heat or thirst
but lack of food
So，how on earth
does a plant
eater this size
survive in a place
apparently
totally devoid of vegetation？
Elephants
in Namibia
are the
toughest in Africa
and they
need to be
What little food
exists is so dispersed
that these elephants walk up to 50 miles a day
As they travel up
the dry river channels
searching for
something to eat
At times the task
looks truly hopeless
Elephants may
seem out of place in this landscape
但係佢哋唔係唯一嘅
Amazingly
lions
live here too
In savannah country
huge herds of
game support prides
containing
twenty lions or more
But to live here
lions have had
to change their habits
Prides are
much smaller
and their home
ranges are very much bigger
And there's an
added problem
Their food is
always on the move
Like the elephants
the lions must
travel great distances
to find
enough to live on
But lions can'
t go everywhere
They won't attempt to cross this field of sand dunes
And the
oryx know it
The lions must wait for the oryx to leave the safety of the dunes
which eventually
they must to find food and water
And then the
lions will ambush them
The elephants
have found some of their favourite food
Grasses are the
staple diet of all elephants
But this herd
concentrates on digging up the roots
Which have more
nutrition and moisture than the stems
It's the sort
of behaviour
that can make all
the difference in a pace of serious shortages
Yet all this can
change in an instant
The fortunes of
many deserts are ruled by distant rains
This water fell as rain in mountains more than a hundred miles away
It's known as
a flash flood
and called that
because the water
may run for just a single day
It's an event
that only happens once or twice a year
at the most
The sandy riverbed acts like a giant strip of blotting paper
sucking up the
water as soon as it appears
But every square
metre of soil moistened by this river
will increase the
chances of survival
for those
that live here
Water holes are
filled temporarily
Elsewhere
in Africa
elephants
drink every day
But the lack
of water here
means that desert
elephants can only refill their tanks
once every
four or five days
Within a week
the flash flood
has produced a flush of green
More than enough
to draw the oryx out of the dunes
It's a rare chance for them to build up their food reserves
The flood has
made life easier for the lions too
The flesh of this oryx will keep the family going for a week at the most
But for a while
the hunting
will be easier
Now that the
river channel has turned green
The good times
for lions and oryx are brief
But these are
the short moments
That make it possible to live in deserts the year round
Death Valley is
the hottest place on earth
Yet even this
furnace can be transformed by water
A single shower can enable seeds that have lain dormant for 30 years or more
to burst
into life
And there hasn't
been a bloom like this one for a century
The periods of
boom in Death Valley are short
But they're just
frequent enough to keep life ticking over
A sudden flush
of vegetation
Is what every
desert dweller waits for
And when
it happens
they must make
the most of it
There is no other
species on the planet
That responds as
quickly and as dramatically
to the good times
as the
desert locust
Eggs that have
remained in the ground for twenty years
begin to hatch
The young locusts
are known as hoppers
for at this stage
they're flightless
They find new
feeding grounds
by following the
smell of sprouting grass
Normally
it takes four
weeks for hoppers to become adults
But when the
conditions are right
as now
their development
switches to the fast track
As the vegetation
in one place begins to run out
The winged adults
release pheromones
scent messages
which tell others
in the group that they must move on
And when
groups merge
they form a swarm
An adult locust
eats its entire body weight every day
and a whole swarm
can consume literally hundreds of tons of vegetation
They have to
keep on moving
The swarm
travels with the wind
It's the most
energysaving way of flying
Following the
flow of wind
means that they'
re always heading toward areas of low pressure
Places where
wind meets rain
and vegetation
starts to grow
As they fly
swarms join up
with other swarms
to form gigantic
plagues several billion strong
and as much as
40 miles wide
They will consume
every edible thing
that lies
in their path
This is one of
planet Earth's greatest spectacles
It's rarely
seen on this scale
and it won'
t last long
Once the
food has gone
the steady roar
of a billion beating locust wings
Will once
again be replaced
By nothing more
than the sound
Of the desert wind